 <chapter id="graphs-plots"><title>Graphs and plots</title>

  <sect1 id="gnuplot-graphs"><title>Gnuplot graphs</title>

    <para>A separate program, namely gnuplot, is called to generate
      graphs. Gnuplot is a very full-featured graphing program with
      myriad options. It is available from <ulink
	url="http://www.gnuplot.org/">gnuplot.org</ulink> (but note
      that a copy of gnuplot is bundled with the MS Windows version of
      <application>gretl</application>).
      <application>gretl</application> gives you direct access, via a
      graphical interface, to only a small subset of gnuplot's options
      but it tries to choose sensible values for you; it also allows
      you to take complete control over graph details if you
      wish.</para>

    <para>Under MS Windows you can click at the top left corner of a
      graph window for a pull-down gnuplot menu that lets you choose
      various things (including copying the graph to the Windows
      clipboard and sending it to a printer).</para>

    <para>For full control over a graph, follow this procedure:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Close the graph window.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>From the Session menu, choose <quote>Add last
	    graph</quote>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>In the session icon window, right-click on the
	  new graph icon and choose either <quote>Edit using
	    GUI</quote> or <quote>Edit plot
	    commands</quote>.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The <quote>Edit using GUI</quote> item pops up a graphical
      controller for gnuplot which lets you fine-tune various aspects
      of the graph.  The <quote>Edit plot commands</quote> item opens
      an editor window containing the actual gnuplot command file for
      generating the graph: this gives you full control over graph
      details &mdash; if you know something about gnuplot. To find out
      more, see the gnuplot <ulink
	url="http://ricardo.ecn.wfu.edu/gnuplot.html">online
	manual</ulink> or <ulink
	url="http://www.gnuplot.org/">gnuplot.org</ulink>.</para>

    <para>See also the entry for <command>gnuplot</command> in 
      <xref linkend="cmdref"/> below &mdash; and the
      <command>graph</command> and <command>plot</command> commands
      for <quote>quick and dirty</quote> ASCII graphs.</para>

    <figure id="fig-plot" float="1" pgwide="1">
      <title>gretl's gnuplot controller</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>gnuplot controller</screeninfo>
	<graphic fileref="figures/plot_control" align="center"/>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="boxplots"><title>Boxplots</title>

    <para>Boxplots are not generated using gnuplot, but rather by
      <application>gretl</application> itself.</para>

    <para>These plots (after Tukey and Chambers) display the
      distribution of a variable. The central box encloses the middle
      50 percent of the data, i.e. it is bounded by the first and
      third quartiles.  The <quote>whiskers</quote> extend to the
      minimum and maximum values.  A line is drawn across the box at
      the median.</para> 

    <para>In the case of notched boxes, the notch shows the limits of
      an approximate 90 percent confidence interval.  This is obtained
      by the bootstrap method, which can take a while if the data
      series is very long.</para>

    <para>Clicking the mouse in the boxplots window brings up a menu
      which enables you to save the plots as encapsulated postscript
      (EPS) or as a full-page postscript file.  Under the X window
      system you can also save the window as an XPM file; under MS
      Windows you can copy it to the clipboard as a bitmap.  The menu
      also gives you the option of opening a summary window which
      displays five-number summaries (minimum, first quartile, median,
      third quartile, maxmimum), plus a confidence interval for the
      median if the <quote>notched</quote> option was chosen.
    </para>

    <para>Some details of gretl's boxplots can be controlled via a
      (plain text) file named <filename>.boxplotrc</filename> which is
      looked for, in turn, in the current working directory, the
      user's home directory (corresponding to the environment variable
      <envar>HOME</envar>) and the gretl user directory (which is
      displayed and may be changed under the <quote>File, Preferences,
	General</quote> menu).  Options that can be set in this way
      are the font to use when producing postscript output (must be a
      valid generic postscript font name; the default is Helvetica),
      the size of the font in points (also for postscript output;
      default is 12), the minimum and maximum for the y-axis range,
      the width and height of the plot in pixels (default, 560 x 448),
      whether numerical values should be printed for the quartiles and
      median (default, don't print them), and whether outliers (points
      lying beyond 1.5 times the interquartile range from the central
      box) should be indicated separately (default, no).  Here is an
      example:</para>

    <programlisting>
font = Times-Roman
fontsize = 16
max = 4.0
min = 0
width = 400
height = 448
numbers = %3.2f
outliers = true
    </programlisting>

    <para>On the second to last line, the value associated with
      <literal>numbers</literal> is a <quote>printf</quote> format
      string as in the C programming language; if specified, this
      controls the printing of the median and quartiles next to the
      boxplot, if no <literal>numbers</literal> entry is given these
      values are not printed.  In the example, the values will be
      printed to a width of 3 digits, with 2 digits of precision
      following the decimal point.</para>

    <para>Not all of the options need be specified, and the order
      doesn't matter.  Lines not matching the pattern <quote>key =
	value</quote> are ignored, as are lines that begin with the
      hash mark, <literal>#</literal>.</para>

    <para>After each variable specified in the boxplot command, a
      parenthesized boolean expression may be added, to limit the
      sample for the variable in question.  A space must be inserted
      between the variable name or number and the expression.  Suppose
      you have salary figures for men and women, and you have a dummy
      variable <literal>GENDER</literal> with value 1 for men and 0
      for women.  In that case you could draw comparative boxplots
      with the following line in the boxplots dialog:</para>
    <programlisting>
      salary (GENDER=1) salary (GENDER=0)
    </programlisting>

  </sect1>

  </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../manual.ced"
mode: xml
sgml-parent-document:("../manual.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

