<?PSGML NOFILL programlisting example informalequation?>

  <chapter id="getting-started"><title>Getting started</title>

  <para>This introduction is mostly angled towards the graphical
    client program; please see <xref linkend="cmdref"/> and
      <xref linkend="cli"/>  below for details on the command-line
    program, <application>gretlcli</application>.
  </para>

  <para>
      You can supply the name of a data file to open as an argument to
    <application>gretl</application>, but for the moment let's not do
    that: just fire up the program.<footnote><para>For convenience
	I will refer to the graphical client program simply as
	<application>gretl</application> in this manual. Note,
	however, that the specific name of the program differs
	according to the computer platform.  On unix-like systems it
	is called <filename>gretl_x11</filename> while on MS Windows
	it is <filename>gretlw32.exe</filename>. On unix-like systems
	a wrapper script named <filename>gretl</filename> is also
	installed &mdash; see also <xref
	  linkend="optarg"/>.</para></footnote> You should see a main
    window (which will hold information on the data set but which is
    at first blank) and various menus, some of them disabled at first.
  </para>

  <para>
    What can you do at this point?  You can browse the supplied data
    files (or databases), open a data file, create a new data file,
    read the help items, or open a command script.  For now let's
    browse the supplied data files.  Under the File menu choose
    <quote>Open data, sample file, Ramanathan&hellip;</quote>.  A
    second window should open, presenting a list of data files
    supplied with the package (see <xref linkend="fig-datafiles"/>).
    The numbering of the files corresponds to the chapter organization
    of Ramanathan (2002), which contains discussion of the analysis of
    these data. The data will be useful for practice purposes even
    without the text.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig-datafiles" float="1" pgwide="1">
    <title>Practice data files window</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Practice data files window</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="figures/datafiles" align="center"/>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
    If you select a row in this window and click on
    <quote>Info</quote> this pops open the the <quote>header
      file</quote> for the data set in question, which tells you
    something about the source and definition of the variables.  If
    you find a file that is of interest, you may open it by clicking
    on <quote>Open</quote>, or just double-clicking on the file name.
    For the moment let's open <filename>data3-6</filename>.
  </para>

  <tip>
    <para>In <application>gretl</application> windows containing
      lists, double-clicking on a line launches a default action for
      the associated list entry: e.g. displaying the values of a data
      series, opening a file.</para>
  </tip>

  <para>
      This file contains data pertaining to a classic econometric
    <quote>chestnut</quote>, the consumption function.  The data
    window should now display the name of the current data file, the
    overall data range and sample range, and the names of the
    variables along with brief descriptive tags &mdash; see
      <xref linkend="fig-mainwin"/>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig-mainwin" float="1" pgwide="1">
    <title>Main window, with a practice data file open</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Main window</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="figures/mainwin" align="center"/>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
      OK, what can we do now?  Hopefully the various menu options
    should be fairly self explanatory.  For now we'll dip into the
    Model menu; a brief tour of all the main window menus is given in
    <xref linkend="menus"/> below.
  </para>

  <para>
    <application>gretl</application>'s Model menu offers numerous
    various econometric estimation routines.  The simplest and most
    standard is Ordinary Least Squares (OLS). Selecting OLS pops up a
    dialog box calling for a <emphasis>model specification</emphasis>
    &mdash; see <xref linkend="fig-selector"/>.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig-selector" float="1" pgwide="1">
    <title>Model specification dialog</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Model specification dialog</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="figures/selector" align="center"/>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>
    To select the dependent variable, highlight the variable you
    want in the list on the left and either click the
    <quote>Choose</quote> button that points to the Dependent variable
    slot or double-click on the variable.  If you check the <quote>Set
      as default</quote> box this variable will be pre-selected as
    dependent when you next open the model dialog box. To select
    independent variables, highlight them on the left and click the
    <quote>Add</quote> button (or click the right mouse button over
    the highlighted variable).  To select several variable in the list
    box, drag the mouse over them; to select several non-contiguous
    variables, hold down the <literal>Ctrl</literal> key and click on
    the variables you want.
  </para>

  <figure id="fig-selector" float="1" pgwide="1">
    <title>Model specification dialog</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Model specification dialog</screeninfo>
      <graphic fileref="figures/selector" align="center"/>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>To run a regression with consumption as the dependent variable
    and income as independent, click <varname>Ct</varname> into the
    Dependent slot and add <varname>Yt</varname> to the Independent
    variables list.</para>

  <sect1 id="est-output"><title>Estimation output</title>

    <para>
      Once you've specified a model, a window displaying the
      regression output will appear.  The output is reasonably
      comprehensive and in a standard format (<xref 
	  linkend="fig-modelwin"/>).
    </para>  

    <figure id="fig-modelwin" float="1" pgwide="1">
      <title>Model output window</title>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Model window</screeninfo>
	<graphic fileref="figures/modelwin" align="center"/>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>The output window contains menus that allow you to inspect
      or graph the residuals and fitted values, and to run various
      diagnostic tests on the model.</para>  

    <para>There is also an option to reprint the regression output in
      &latex; format.  This is not fully implemented yet, but works
      for OLS models.  You can print the results in a tabular format
      (similar to what's in the output window, but properly typeset)
      or as an equation, across the page.  For each of these options
      you can choose to preview the typeset product, or save the
      output to file for incorporation in a &latex; document.
      Previewing requires that you have a functioning &tex; system on
      your computer.</para> 

    <para>If you want to import <application>gretl</application>
      output into an editor or word processor there are two main
      options.  You can simply copy and paste from an output window
      (using its <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem> menu) to the target
      program, or you can save the output to a file then import the
      file into the target program.  When you finish a
      <application>gretl</application> session you are given the
      option of saving all the output from the session to a single
      file.</para>

    <tip><para>When inserting <application>gretl</application> output
	into a word processor, select a monospaced or typewriter-style
	font (e.g. Courier) to preserve the output's tabular
	formatting.  Select a small font (10-point Courier should do)
	to prevent the output lines from being broken in the wrong
	place.</para>
    </tip>

  </sect1>
  </chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
sgml-default-dtd-file:"../manual.ced"
mode: xml
sgml-parent-document:("../manual.xml" "book" "chapter")
End:
-->

